hello I'm Jackie Johnson and today we
will be discussing typhoid mary let's
travel back to 1900 New York City
immigrants were just flooding in from
all over the world to start their new
life in America and then we see one
angel face and she says I'm Mary Mallon
I am Irish I'm proud and I'm here to
cook baby so um
Mary's signature dish was vanilla ice
cream with sliced peaches the rich
people would call up their friends and
say honey have you had Mary Mallon's
peach vanilla ice cream it is the best
friggin dessert that's how she got
around word-of-mouth old-school
marketing so uh what is it Easter Bay
Oyster Bay is like the Beverly Hills of
the time Teddy Roosevelt's there that's
where he summers Charles Warren is there
he is the banker to all the rich people
including their Vanderbilt's so what
happens to his family Dave all of a
sudden gets sick and they say we're rich
we don't have to deal with disease dr.
George Soper rolls up his job is
whatever a sanitation engineer is dr.
Soper says well honey I'll be honest
everybody in your family is type of a
fever Charles says what what does that
mean type typhoid and in dr. Soper says
you could hemorrhage from the inside
people died from this
this is 1900 we don't have pills we
don't have what we don't have
what's it called what's that pill that
solves everything antibiotics we didn't
have that okay
there's no antibiotics okay so Charles
Warren says here's a bunch of money hunt
down the source and kill it all dr.
Sopher gets to business he goes through
the plumbing he interviews the local
fishmonger he's trying to find the
typhoid and finding dead ends everywhere
he goes but then all of a sudden he gets
a call from Manhattan there's a wealthy
family who just came down with typhoid
the little girl is very sick she has her
covers up to her face she says daddy I'm
cold
I'm very cool daddy so Soper rolls up
and interviews the family he realizes
they just had a new chef he's just wait
a minute who was a chef they said well
she was a delightful Irish immigrant
named Mary Mallon this over says wait a
damn minute that's the same woman who
was cooking for the family choice term a
and he says I think we're on to
something baby I think I'm on to
something
so anyway supper rolls up to Mary's
house he says excuse me ma'am I'm pretty
sure you have typhoid fever and I'm
pretty sure you're giving it to
everybody that you're cooking for
and she says excuse me I am an Irish
immigrant woman trying to make it in
1900 New York how dare you accuse me of
being unsanitary then she chases him out
with a fork
he says if you ever come back if you
ever try to pull my money again I will
take you out so he needs to get more
evidence he sits down on his desk there
papers everywhere and he says oh my
eight families merry mounters cook for
seven of them have contracted typhoid
that's not a coincidence
that's not that is fat honey it happens
you know what else happens hmm
great know where you are let's see
cuz you know the brains fading I'll be
honest the brain is going out I love
that you're always honest okay
so we are pissed at this point the
health inspector add dr. Soper roll-up
to marys they bust over the door and
they said Mary
we have unequivocal proof that your
spread died point all over this damn
city what is the deal she says honey
you're making up I'm fine and they
say Mary are you washing your hands
after you take a be honest she says
if I'm being honest no I don't wash my
hands thoroughly every time I take a
dump I'm a busy woman I'm trying to get
dessert made I'm trying to get the
appetizers done so sometimes I gotta
take a while I'm at work I hurry up
I wipe and I give back in that kitchen
okay time is money and I'm trying to
make my damn money
they said you're making rich people sick
that's unacceptable so they grabbed her
by her infested wrists and they
ship her off to North Brother Island
which is where they quarantine people
with diseases
Mary Mallon sits on the damn Island
alone with her dog for three years
meanwhile they test her sweat her spit
her do skits their cheese her I juice
did it over a hundred tests in the all
tests positive for typhoid fever yet she
showed no symptoms
finally the health inspector says listen
Mary I'll level with you okay we want
you to get out of here
but you gotta wash your damn hands and
you gotta promise that you're not gonna
cook
she says and they say okay pinkie swear
marry she says pinkie swear health
inspector we sick of her dance
so she pieces out on the island
everything's fine New York is
flourishing five years later in 1915
there is a typhoid outbreak at Sloane
Maternity Hospital two people died at
the hospital
- so sober rolls up to the hospital a
nurse who's very sick says we're clean
we're a hospital we're not idiots we
know how to not get typhoid yet we all
got it what's happening he says wait a
minute
who's a cook here baby who's the cook
well it's just delightful Irish woman
named Mary Brown who's in the damn
kitchen of hospital Derek take a wild
guess
George storms into the kitchen he
thoughts open the damn door and his foot
as a power mode he says I see you Mary
Mallon I see you I see you and I smell
you I caught you fecal matter handed
baby I caught you fecal matter Panda
they took her back to North Brother
Island twenty-three years she's sat in
quarantine and in nineteen oh my
pillow hold on let me put my pillow back
cuz I love a good throw mo I love a good
in accent pillow okay in 1938 Mary
dollars the minute her body hit the
ground they sliced her open pulled out
that gallbladder what did they see my
typhoid virus dr. subra was like I knew
it I knew it what have I been
saying
what have I been saying an asymptomatic
carrier of typhoid has been living among
us for years this is crazy but you know
what is America baby
the land of crazy and the land of
opportunity okay the medical journals
all start calling her typhoid mary so
she is considered to be the first
asymptomatic case of type with fever in
history of the planet how insane is that
honestly if you could tell Mary one
thing right now I would tell Mary make
your money make your ice cream make a
career and a life for yourself but honey
wash your in hands
you